Have you
ever seen high school sports like this?
It's a pain endurance game.
You hop on your knuckles.
Ready? Hop!
It's done on closed fist.
And so as you hop over the hardwood
floor, you get bloody knuckles.
This is the seal hop.
It's one of a series of gruelling
physical and mental challenges
that make up the NYO Games.
Anchorage, Alaska.
A modern city home to a fusion of cultures.
Where the high life meets
the wildlife, and pride in the past
inspires the present and the future.
And home to the NYO Games.
Bringing together athletes
from all over the state
for three days of intense competition.
But this is no ordinary high school
sports tournament.
They're more than just games.
They're about survival.
Athletes compete in a series of events
each of which has its own backstory
based on real life survival skills.
We'll be finding out all
about the surprising origins of the games
and hearing
from some of the athletes taking part.
But first, let's find out how the
NYO Games got started.
And who better to tell us that
than Kyle Worl?
He grew up around the games.
My dad was an athlete in the 80s and 90s.
Now he's an athlete himself
as well as a coach and mentor
to the next generation.
But it's okay. We've practiced.
These games have always been played
in our communities for hundreds of years.
They were played during the winter months.
It was too dark or cold or
the weather was too severe to go outside.
And so the games were a way to pass time.
And we brought it into the modern age.
The first NYO Games in 1971 saw 12 schools
Participate.
And now? There are over 50 teams
and almost 475 athletes.
This is head official Nicole Johnson.
She's been attending the games
for more than 40 years.
My first NYO was in 1982
as a seventh grader. From high school
I started coaching.
From coaching
I moved into an official position.
And in 2004
I became NYO Games Alaska's head official.
Nearly every single tribe
in the state of Alaska sends a team.
And there are, I believe, 270
different tribes
within the state of Alaska.
Today, the games are a way of sharing
and celebrating native traditions.
Long ago, and still today, our people
live off the land.
They hunt, they fish, they gather.
And it's not always an easy lifestyle.
And so the games were intentionally made
to challenge you physically and mentally
so you that when you were faced
with situations - whether it was out
in a snowstorm or even enduring pain -
these games were a way to prepare you
for those situations.
Every event at the NYO Games has a story.
Here are just a few of them.
The Intuit Stick Pull is a contest
of sheer strength and determination.
Contestants try to pull their
opponent up off the floor,
or pull the stick away from their opponent,
without jerking, twisting,
or adjusting their grip.
So when you come across a seal,
you harpoon the seal,
and then you pull out that harpoon.
And so the Inuit Stick Pull represents
that motion of pulling in a seal.
They can be 700 pounds or more.
And so that's a tough battle.
If you let go, that's your food, right?
Your family goes hungry.
So you really unlock
another level of strength.
The One-Foot High Kick demands
strength, flexibility and balance.
From a standing or running start,
athletes jump with both feet,
kick a suspended ball with one foot,
then land on the kicking foot.
Out on the tundra it's really flat.
And on a clear day
you could see someone on the horizon.
And a high kick was used as sign language
back before we had radios or cell phones.
And it was a way to signal either
A successful or unsuccessful hunt.
And finally we have the Seal Hop.
The most physically and mentally demanding
of all the events,
athletes must maintain a lowered
push up position with elbows bent,
hands curled and knuckles down.
At the official’s signal
contestants hop across the floor,
mimicking the movement of a seal.
The reason they would do this is
because as hunters,
we had to figure out how to get close
enough to the seal without scaring it off.
That was their trick
to get close enough to the seal, jump up
with the harpoon, and they'd have a seal
to bring home to your community.
And it's a very challenging one.
You get bloody hands from it.
Now we've learned about the games
it's time to meet some of the student
athletes taking part.
My name is Don Heflin.
Inupiaq
from my mom's side, from Nome, Alaska.
My name is Leif Richards.
I live in Juneau
but my family's from the village of Igiugig.
My name's Mila Neely.
I'm a citizen of the Cherokee Nation and
I was born and raised in Juneau, Alaska.
I compete in a couple of different events.
I compete in the One-Foot High Kick,
Two-Foot High Kick,
Scissor Broad Jump,
Toe Kick, Kneel Jump and Seal Hop.
I compete in all the games
but this year at State I competed
in the One-Foot High Kick, the One-Arm Reach and Scissor Broad.
I compete in a lot of different events.
I do all three kicking events:
One-Foot, Two-Foot,
Alaskan, I do Wrist Carry,
Dene, Stick Pull.
What am I forgetting? Oh, Seal Hop!
That's one of my favorites.
I like Seal Hope because it's like an
endurance game and it's at the very end.
It's just, like, all the leftover energy
you have, just like all out.
I think if my ancestors and family
were here seeing me do these games
I think they would be really proud of me
because that means I'm still
celebrating our culture.
I do feel connected to the history.
All the games are about survival
and helping each other out. Doing the games
makes me feel very connected
to the community and my culture.
It really connects me even though I'm not
Alaska Native, I'm Cherokee.
It kind of helps
connect me to my indigenous roots.
I think if
someone from a different part of the world
saw us doing NYO of it would kind of, like,
inspire them.
Our people had to be very resilient,
Strong, tough people.
And these games were all created
to help develop
those skills that they needed to survive.
Joining NYO was really life changing
because it was a space where I didn't
have to hide my indigenous identity.
I was able to
really build my own confidence and connect
with my native identity
in a positive way.
I feel a greater sense
of belonging in my community,
A sense of purpose.
And I have these games to thank.
You good?
I’m proud of you.